<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to a paper; called, A petition of one Thomas Ellyson, late shepherd of Easington in the county of Durham, to his Highness the Lord Protector of England, Scotland and Ireland, and to all emperors, kings and princes through the world.</title>
            <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E814_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207351</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866408</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 124:E814[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to a paper; called, A petition of one Thomas Ellyson, late shepherd of Easington in the county of Durham, to his Highness the Lord Protector of England, Scotland and Ireland, and to all emperors, kings and princes through the world.</title>
                  <author>Howgill, Francis, 1618-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Francis Howgill.</note>
                  <note>A reply to Ellyson, Thomas. To his Highness, Oliver, Lord Protector.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ellyson, Thomas. --  To his Highness, Oliver, Lord Protector --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118680:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A PAPER; CALLED, <hi>A Petition of one</hi> Thomas Ellyſon, <hi>late Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of Eaſingion in the County of Durham, to his Highneſs the Lord Protector of England, Scotland and Ireland, and to all Emperors, Kings and Princes through the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:118680:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118680:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ANSWER TO A PAPER: CALLED,</hi> A Petition of one <hi>Thomas Ellyſon,</hi> late Shepherd of <hi>Eaſinton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> to his Highneſs the Lord Protector of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to all Emperors, Kings and Princes through the world.</head>
            <p>THere are many in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> that know that thou haſt been a Shepherd lately enough, and ſee thee what thou haſt been, and where thou haſt been, and where thou art now; and knows thee to be one in nature with thoſe Shepherds which the Lord ſent <hi>Ezekiel, Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to cry againſt, who feeds them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the fat, and cloathes themſelves with the wool; and that thou art one of thoſe Shepherds that cares not for the ſheep, and art in the nature of one of thoſe Shepherds which the true Prophets cryed againſt, which were as even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves, and as Foxes in the deſert: And for the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake, I am moved to lay open thy deceit, that thou art one of thoſe Foxes thou ſpeaks of, which hath fire in their tails; and thou are made manifeſt to be of old <hi>Cains</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that old murthering ſpirit; and with thy flattering titles which thon gives to men, and hath mens perſons in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion becauſe of advantage, and thou art born after the fleſh, the ſon of the bond-woman, who art petitioning to men that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118680:3"/>
they may abuſe their power, and exalt themſelves over the heritage of God; and thou that wouldſt have Laws to bind the conſciences of men to walk after thy will, thou art Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and thou that art petitioning the Powers of the earth to make Laws to limit the Holy One of Iſral: But bleſſed be the Lord, the day is come that thou and all deceivers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors and flatterers is diſcovered; and many ſees thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Majeſtrates, that thy ſpirit is the ſame that would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand fire to come down from heaven to have deſtroyed them who would not receive them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou ſaith <hi>That Moſes, who was a Commander over all Iſrael, that he was appointed to bear the people in his boſom as a nurſing father; and thou ſaith, thou art a cryer for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe things, that all might be carried in their arms now; and thou goes on and tells them that God will require the Government of his Church at their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep. Moſes,</hi> who was faithful and true over the houſe of God, who was a figure of Chriſt, he did receive the Law from the mouth of the Lord, he acted in righteouſneſs; and when <hi>Elead</hi> and <hi>Madad</hi> propheſied, he was not angry, as thou art; but deſired that all the Lords people were Prophets; and all who wait upon the Lord, to receive the Law of God from his mouth now, and walk in the ſame, they have the ſame ſpirit, and they will not limit the holy One: But thy cry that thou calleſt for is, that thou wouldſt have them who are in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtead, as thou ſaith they are, for to limit the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly One. And thou art the deceiver the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, which is gone into the world, who would perſwade the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtrates that they muſt govern the Church; and ſo thou wouldeſt have this generation of Rulers to be daſh'd in pieces as all the generations have been before them, in exalting themſelves in the ſeat of Chriſt: when as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>The government is upon Chriſts ſhoulders:</hi> and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He alone treads the Wine-preſs:</hi> And therefore whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will aſſume unto themſelves; to govern the Church by an outward, viſible; carnal Law, ſhall be as ſure to be broken as all the reſt. The Church is in God, and is inviſible; and that which is viſible and natural cannot make any law to bind
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118680:3"/>
that which is unlimited: but they if they doe go about to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and would ſet themſelvs in his ſeat of Judgment, and take away his glory which he will not give to any; and all ſuch as have made any laws in their own wills to limit ſons and daughters, they have all been broken as the Scripture witneſſeth every where: and therfore let all Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all the world to whom thou writeſt, take heed how they ſet themſelves in the room of God, and lay yokes upon the necks of them who are free by the Son, and are brought by the power of the Lord from under the breach of all righteous Laws, or tranſgreſſing any holy, &amp; which is juſt: for the law is for the lawleſs law not for them who are in righteouſneſs, but the law is for the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsors who are in unrighteouſneſs and they are thoſe that act by that Spirit which dwells in thee, who would levy troops for the Innocent; and art wroth, and thy countenance falls like <hi>Cain</hi> and hates thy brethren, and would haue a law made over the conſcience, and would have the Powers of the earth to abuſe their power, in turning their ſwords againſt them who live in righteouſnes, and declare againſt unrighteouſnes.</p>
            <p>And further thou goeſt on and telleſt them, this was a law given to <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo thou perverteſt the Scripture by thy imaginations: Where readeſt thou of ſuch a law given to <hi>Adam,</hi> that he compelled his family to religion? And further thou ſayeſt, Which care of government is in great neglect in this Nation; upon reſpect to tender conſciences, ſundry Sects and ſorts of Schiſmaticks are ſuffered unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and they ſacrifice to <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> And thou goeſt on and telleſt the Nobles, that it lies upon their ſcore that they ſhould ſuppreſs them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which was given to a particular family or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which was for its time, is not everlaſting. So any that takes up any rule without them to act by, acts not by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, but by tradition in their own wills, God abhors that. And thou bringeſt in the Old-Covenant which was given to a particular people the Jews, but now the Prieſthood is changed, and the Law is changed; and as for thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> law which thou wouldſt have the Governors of this Nation to make for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118680:4"/>
ſuppreſſing of Sects and Schiſmaticks that worſhip at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and thou ſayeſt this is charged upon them. But thou mightſt have told them who they had been, and where <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> is, leſt they be miſtaken as thou art, that cals darkneſs light, and light darkneſs. But all that thou art troubled at is this, that the light of Chriſt in the conſcience ſhould have liberty; and here thou art he which is born after the fleſh, and art that Egyptian thou ſpeaks of, which perſecutes the righteous ſeed. It is true, there are Sects and Schiſms too many, and Opinions, they ſtand all in one ground, and thou and they come out of one land, <hi>Babylon</hi> is the land of your nativity; in the light you are ſeen, that thou and they are turned from the light of Chriſt, and ſo are gone into ſects and opinions and imaginations, and all the powers without in the world cannot ſuppreſs the root from whence theſe flow, none can overcome the root from whence hereſies and opinions come. And therefore, vain Shepherd and blind, ceaſe thy divining: Thoſe that thou woulſt have ſuppreſt, are thoſe that break bread from houſe to houſe, and meet together in the name of the Lord, as the Saints ever did, and this thou calleſt <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> becauſe they will not come to an Idols temple where all the deceived in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worſhip an unknown God. I ſay unto thee, thy Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, thy Idols temple which God never commanded, where all lyars, and fighters, and ſwearers, and night-birds and Scriech-owls meet, and call it the houſe of God, and where they ſpeak nought but the imaginations of their own hearts, and call them the ordinances of God, and it the Church, that's <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> And as for the Magiſtrates which thou telleſt they ought to ſuppreſs the falſe Prophets, thou mightſt have declared who they had been. But for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt-hearted Magiſtracie and people, I ſhall declare a little when they came in, and who they are. Chriſt ſayes, many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe; and <hi>Paul, Peter, John,</hi> and and the reſt, they ſaw them come already then, many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, deceivers, and then they came in as the Scriptures witneſs, and they have deceived the Nations ſince; and Chriſt ſaith, by their fruits you ſhall know them; and they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118680:4"/>
are ſuch as he cryed wo againſt, which laid heavy burthens upon the people, and ſuch as were got into <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, and were called of men maſter, ſtood praying in the Aſſemblies, and had the chiefeſt place in the ſynagogue; and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith they followed after covetous practiſes; and <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith they went after the error of Balaam for gifts and rewards; and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſays they ſought for their gain, for their quarter; and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith, they were ſuch as fed of the fat; and <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaith they were as evening wolves; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith they were covetous men, heady, highminded, and lovers of pleaſure, and fierce deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, aad had a form of godlineſs, and they were witches that turned them back to circumciſion, and falſe Prophets when the ſubſtance was come. And are they not ſo now, who ſue for Tythes, maintain the firſt Prieſthood, and bewitch people, and deny Chriſt come in the fleſh? Now let all judge where theſe are, many in the North taking away the peoples Cows, their pots and kettles, and b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dding, and one Prieſt ſued one for two pence, and two in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> ſued one for one penny, and another for a penny halfpenny; and theſe are they that call themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel. Shame, ſhame, bluſh, houl you Caterpillars, the hand of the Lord is againſt you. And yet I would not have their lives taken away, as thou wouldſt have theirs that thou callſt Sectaries: but to that in thy conſcience I ſpeak, which will let thee ſee that thou haſt a buſie mind, and abideſt not in the doctrine of Chriſt, but art amongſt the falſe Prophers.</p>
            <p>And thou and the reſt of them which are Merchants, and tradeſt with other mens words, which muſt have your Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and your Worſhip defended with ſwords and Staves, and the power of the earth, you are they that ſpread nets at <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peh</hi> and <hi>Tabor;</hi> for its neither in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> nor this Mount, but they that worſhip the Father, worſhip in ſpirit and truth, and thou that woulſt confine God to a place, to a day, to a time, and have him bound by a Law and the Saints how they ſhall worſhip him: thou art carnall, and thy petition carnall, and all who have any honeſty in them or light, will ſee thee to be in the generation of the Phariſees, that ſaid they had a Law, and by that law he ought to die.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118680:5"/>And whereas thou art comparing thy ſelf and the Prieſts of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and <hi>Durham</hi> to <hi>Sarah</hi> the Miſtreis, and them who oppoſe you to <hi>Hagar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw: Sarah</hi> never brought forth ſons of Bondage, as you are, but you are truly <hi>Hagar</hi> the <hi>Egiptian</hi> who g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nders unto bondage for you and all the children that ever you have begotten or brought forth, are in bondage till now, and the Lord hath raiſed up a people out of the Duſt, to confound you and your wiſdom, and to declare againſt your profſſi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on in laying heavie burdens upon the people, and taking their money for that which is not bread and be ye all aſhamed ye high Okes, ye fat Bulls, ye Diviners, that cannot maintain y<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u Goſpel with all your parts and wiſdom that you boaſt of, againſt thoſe contemptible things in your eyes, but you muſt run to a carnall Sword, or to a Juſtice of Peace, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable to preſerve you, or to have them impriſoned, ſtocks &amp; mockings, and reproaches, this is all we have or expect from the Powers of the earth, becauſe we ſpeak the truth: Be ye aſhamed, and lay your hands upon your mouths; what Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is this they have preached? what Worſhip is this you give unto God that muſt be defended with clubs and Staves, and Stocks and whips, ſtoning and haling before Magiſtrates, and yet thou wouldſt have them accounted Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, they who were Miniſters of the Goſpel their weapons were not carnall but ſpiritual and they were mighty through God, but the mightineſs of this generation lies in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſword to defend them, and drive the people to pay them mony for nought. And therefore let all Magiſtrates conſider in this Nation and elſwhere, that you be warned how you make any laws againſt the innocent, and how you uphold thoſe that Chriſt cried woe againſt, and ſuch as the Lord ſent his Prophets to declare againſt, leſt that come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them which the Prophet ſpoke, that they that help and them that are helped ſhall fall tog<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou further flatte<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s them, and tells them that they are in the room of <hi>Abraham</hi> for ordering the houſe of God, to ſee that the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac</hi> be inheritors, which is like to be deprived by the Egyptian brood.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118680:5"/>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> My defire is, that they may be guided by the ſpirit of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who denied his country; and if they walk in the light, they will be like him, and will ſee that things be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the Nation in righteouſneſs. But if they will take take thy word who is the <hi>Iſaac</hi> that thou wouldſt ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit, thou wilt preſent them <hi>Iſmael.</hi> But is it not the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of Tythes and Augmentations, and to have people to fall down to worſhip the Image that they have ſet up? that is it thou wouldſt have ordered: For who are of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> are of the ſeed which the promiſe is to; and ſuch you ſtir up the Magiſtrates by your ſlatteries, and lyes, and the people to have a law to keep them in bondage; and ſo to them that dwell in the light, he ſees it is the Egyptian that thou wouldſt have to inherit.</p>
            <p>And further, thou art telling of ſome that profeſs high attainments; which hath put the Kingdom in confuſion and a flame, and thou ſayſt they ought not to ſuffer the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word to go down, nor the Sacraments to fail.</p>
            <p>There is profeſſion enough in the Nation, but little poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; and all who profeſs high things, and do not poſſeſs them, are hypocrites. And now bleſſed be the Lord, Chriſt is come and made manifeſt, which is the higheſt attainment; and he comes not to ſend peace on the earth, but a ſword, and he ſhall confound the mighty and the lofty, and they that have lived at eaſe ſhall be poured from veſſel to veſſel; and now is war proclaimed betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> our Prince, and all the inhabitants of the earth, and all inchanters and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and all ſuch as have made merchandiſe of ſouls, are now made manifeſt; and now the nations are angry, and the men of the earth are afraid, and now <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the Camp of the Saints about, and the Beaſt upon which the Whore rides, and the falſe Prophets, and as many as have traded with the beaſt and the whore are troubled for her ſorrow is coming in a day, and all the powers of the earth cannot nor ſhall not uphold her, for ſhe ſhall be made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and burned with fire; and now thou and the reſt of the merchants are troubled, and are petitioning to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the earth to uphold you: I ſay unto thee, and unto all that<gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118680:6"/>
joyn themſelves againſt the Anointed which is now appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who was dead and is alive, and lives for evermore, You ſhall all be broken, and your eyes ſhall conſume in their holes: Gather your ſelves together, howl ye Caterpillars, ſtrengthen your ſelves, build up your batteries, caſt up your mounts, for a mighty and a terrible one is coming up againſt you; his voice is as the roaring of a Lyon, he is greedy of his prey, he ſhall devour at once, and he is bringing about his determination to cut off every one that withſtands him, and no weapon formed ſhall proſper; the eternal word is preached, and the Angel is flying through the midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the everlaſting Goſpel, and by it ſhall Antichriſt be conſumed. And becauſe this Goſpel is declared and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and witneſſed, thou art angry: But that which thou calls preaching the Word, is nothing but thy own imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This they have preached long enough, and what hath it done, all your divining? None hath been turned from his iniquity. And as for thy Sacrament, thou waſt complaining of the Popes Emiſſaries, and here thou art one. Thou mayſt return thy word back from whence thou hadſt it: and all who come to witneſs the word and the preaching of it; and the body and blood of Chriſt which is the Saints com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and the ſupper of the Lord, will deny all your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment, and all your canker'd ruſty wormeaten divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all powers which ſeek to uphold this which was and is abomination to the Lord, they muſt partake of her plagues; let all conſider God hath overturned all the powers that have pretended to eſtabliſh Religion by a law, when as they have but eſtabliſhed a form, a husk, and ſo Satan hath crept into that; and all the Prieſts in this Nation have they not transformed into every image what way ſoever Authority and the powers of the earth bend, and ſo have made merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and ſold that which is not bread, and ſo have deceived the people.</p>
            <p>And further thou ſayſt, <hi>The Apoſtle requires them to mark them that cauſe diviſions diligently.</hi> And thou goes on and teckons up many that have been polluted in Religion, and thou ſayes he will caſt her into a bed of torment if they do not repent.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118680:6"/>
               <hi>Rep</hi> They who are turned from the light of Chriſt, are turned into diviſion; and they that have not the ſame ſpirit by which the Apoſtle ſpake that ſaid ſo, are divided from Chriſt, and from the body, and from the Saints, and are in contention. And here I charge thee and all the Prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> that you are divided from Chriſt, and turned from the light, who propheſie for hire, and divine for many, who go in long robes, who are called of men moſter, who have the chiefeſt place in the aſſembly, and ſtand praying in the ſynagogue, who go to law with your hearers, and who give meanings upon the Scriptures, who add and diminiſh, who ſpeak but that which you have gathered from other mens words; there doth ſects and opinions, ſtrife and diviſion ariſe. And here thou art marked by many in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> praiſed be the Lord, to be one that is divided from the light, and cauſes diviſion, who took away four Oxen for five pence halfpeny; and ſo they have turned away from thee, and all who ſtand in that nature wherein thou ſtands: And therefore thou art petitioning that thou might have a law to bind us under thy witchcraft, wherein the Nations have been deceived. And it is true, God hath overturned Kings, and Princes, and Dukes, and Earls, and Emperors, for the ſake of his choſen ones; and all they who have made an image like the true God, and like the Goſpel, and have made a decree, and whoſoever now make a decree that any ſhall fall down to worſhip any thing which is contrary to the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, God hath hewed them down, and he will hew them down who go about to limit the Holy One who is Lord over all, and who will have dominion over the conſciences of men; and the time is already when <hi>Jeſabel</hi> is to be caſt into a bed of torment, and all who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fornication with her, whether they be Kings, Emperors, Dukes or Earls, they ſhall all go down with the Dukes of <hi>Edom</hi> into the pit, and with the reſt of the uncircumciſed, and the Saints ſhall rejoice in their overthrow.</p>
            <p>And thou ſays, there is yet little doth appear in <hi>England,</hi> but the old Beaſt under new habits acts his old tragedies; and thou tells of Satans arrowes which are brought into the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118680:7"/>
and thou tells of Kanters and Quakers, and Seekers and Creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, creatures new come from the pit; and thou ſayeſt they reſemble Sampſons foxes which burn up faith bred by hearing the word preacht.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> What haſt thou and they that call themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel preached, and cryed Reformation, and have ſided with all mens wills, and flattered all the Governors and Governments that have been changed divers times within theſe ten years, have you got nothing done yet, but have travailed and brought forth nothing but wind and divifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contention, and one of ſupplanting another? and have you tried one another, and proved one another, and every one preached up what he would have had, and have you brought nought to paſs? what ſhameleſs Reformers are ye? Can you not maintain with your Commiſſions and all your petitioning for Gods Miniſters for the North; and you had your deſire, they came as thick as locuſts out of the South; and cannot you all with your preaching preach down thoſe contemptible creatures that thou ſpeaks of? And as for Ranters, I deny both thee and them, for thou and they ſpring both from one root. And I am one thou calls a Qiaker and Seeker; and bleſſed be the Lord for evermore, that ever <hi>I</hi> was found worthy to qear the name in truth; for they that ſeek ſhall find, and they that wait ſhall not be aſhamed. And thou blind Shepherd, thou might as well have uttered forth thy venom at David, Daniel, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy, and the reſt of the holy men of God, and have ſaid they came out of the pit. Thou proud blaſpheme<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, God will plead with thee for derii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the power of the Lord; and thou ars that Fox thou ſpeaks of, that would be devouring and have all conſumed, that thy corrupt ſenſual fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy will might be ſatisfied: And as for faith, thou never came to the faith of devils, who believe and ttemble; and thy faith and thy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which are but imaginations and traditions of men, the day is diſcnvered that ſhall burn them up and conſume all, and you ſhall be left naked add bare, and have nothing to cover your nakedneſs, but you ſhall be as a ſtink and a proverb.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaith, they preach down Miniſtery and means, and all but thoſe that have knowledg miraculouſly infuſed; and thou art offended, becauſe we declare what the Prophets were when they were called to prophecy; and what the Apoſtles were before they went to preach, and thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thy concluſions, that they will ſend Princes to beg aſwel as the Miniſtery, and thou ſaith, nothing was more ſtrongly charged upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then ſuppreſſing of falſe Prophets; and thou ſaith, ſhall not Chriſtian Princes alſo be zealous to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them that would devour the flock of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>When wilt thou ceaſe thy lying and ſlandering, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt we own and love, which hath not been, nor are not Miniſters made by the will of man, and ſuch have turned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118680:7"/>
away from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan to God, and ſuch a Miniſtry we honor; but all thoſe who ſtand is mans will we deny, and are bold to affirm that they run, and never were ſent, and therefore they do not profit the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and all thy means, and thy mediate choice which is carnal we deny; for none either by you or it, ever had their mindes changed from darkneſs to light, but only brought into a form a husk, a ſhadow, and made hypocrites to profeſs what they were not; and as for thy miraculous infuſion, I deny thy words, but this I ſay, none knows the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him, and that Goſpel that we preach, we neither received it of man, nor from man, but by immediate Revelation, and unto this the Scripture witneſſe: I know Prophets and Miniſters of Chriſt which was Shepherds and gatherers of Summer fruit, and husbandmen at the plow, and the ſame call as ever was: God is not bound up to your trade of Divination and Study and by theſe which are baſe in your eyes ſhall you be confounded, and be broken as a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters veſſell: And for thy concluſion, that we may ſend Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to beg, we deny; we do not diſpute who rule, whether he be a ſhepherd or a husbandman, we know he that fears the Lord is guided by the light of Chriſt, he will walk and act in righteouſneſs, whether he be a Prince or a Plowman; and God is no reſpecter of perſons, nor we reſpect no mans perſon, as thou flatterer doth, but we honor the power that is of God, and are ſubject to it for conſcience ſake, we are not wrangling about the earth, we are redeemed out of it; and as for <hi>Naaſh</hi> thou ſpeaks on, who would ſtrike out the right eye of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou ſhalt ſtand for thy ſelf; for it is the true Iſraelite in whoſe mouth there is no guile, and the Jew inward that thou would not only ſtrike out the eie, but alſo cut off their heads; and who they are that do devour the flock of Chriſt, they are Wolves and deceivers, ſuch as I ſpoke of before, that abideth not in the doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> read tay ſelf there and own it.</p>
            <p>And thou goes on further and Petitions the noble Princes to conſider, that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have mightily prevailed in this Nation, and thou wonders that the Governors have not ſuppreſst, and thou bringſt an old Story to accuſe them with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118680:8"/>
out of <hi>Germany,</hi> That they had plurality of Wives, and this thou ſaith is like to deſtroy the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Thou art <hi>Iſmael</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hagar,</hi> thy hand is againſt every man, and <hi>Cain</hi> is the root from whence thou ſprang, for thou haſt murther in thy heart, and would command fire to come down from heaven to deſtroy, and knows not what ſpirit thou art of, and as for the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> prevailing, here thou haſt made the ſhame of your Miniſtery appear, that it hath had no more effect upon the peoples minds, that they have not bin eſtabliſhed, &amp; ſo they have run after every wind of doctrin; and thou wouldſt have the Magiſtrates to make the people live ſtill upon wind: And as for thy Story of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> concerning the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> I have great ground to believe that thou and thy Author may aſwel belye them which thou never knew, as to lye upon thoſe which are nearer at hand; but if they acted any ſuch thing as plurality of wives, let them bear their own ſhame, do not accuſe the innocent; truly, I know no ſuch <hi>Baptists</hi> in the Nation, and it is no more accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation upon them, then if thou ſhould accuſe the diſciples with <hi>Iudas;</hi> and this thou layeſt upon the Magiſtrate to conſider, leſt the Nation be deſroyed; filthy buſie mind, troubling thy ſelf and others with old Stories raked out of the pit to accuſe others with, when as there is no ſuch thing that is owned, and all who fears the Lord denies ſuch, and I deny them, and they and all who act in uncleanneſs: And thou goes on and ſhews, as thou hath ſtoln from other mens words, from the Prophets and <hi>Moſes,</hi> that the judgment of the Lord was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Idolaters and falſ Prophets and dreamers, and how they &amp; them that ſerved ſtrange <hi>gods</hi> were to be put to death.</p>
            <p>Wo unto them ſaith the Lord, that ſteals my Word every man from his neighbor, and ſay, thus ſaith the Lord, when as the Lord hath never ſpoken unto them; thou haſt ſtoln other mens words, and ſhalt be judged by thy own mouth, and thy own law, that thou never had the word of the Lord made manifeſt, nor never did the Lord ſpeak to thee, but what thou haſt gotten; and therefore thou art that falſ Prophet, and art that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and he that hath a dream, let him tel a dream, and he that hath the word of the Lord, let him ſpeak it; now them that ſpeak the word of the Lord from the mouth of the Lord as the true Prophets did &amp; do, then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118680:8"/>
thou calſt to the Magiſtrates to put them to death: And as for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of ſtrange gods, many in the county of <hi>Durham,</hi> &amp; many other places, let them declare whether they worſhiped any but a ſtrange god at a diſtance, &amp; went after dumb Idols, even as they were led while they followed the Miniſtry which was never ſent; but now is the Lord made manifeſt, and the ſtrange Gods are put away and broken, and the falſe Prophets are ſeen, and the Prophet is raiſed up which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake of, and whoſoever hears not his words, ſhalbe ſlain with a ſword.</p>
            <p>And further thou tels the Magiſtrates, That if any hypocrite ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſpeak a word in the name of the Lord, which he hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Even he ſhall dye, and it is an old ſtatute unrepealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> If thou knew what thou ſpake, thou haſt given ſentence againſt thy ſelf; I charge upon thee in the preſence of the living God, that thou never heard his word, nor ſpake his word but in thy own name; and I charge it again upon thee, when did he ever ſpeak to thee; that ſpirit by which the prophets of the Lord ſpoke thou doſt deride, and calſt it a miraculous Inſuſion, and ſo thy ſpirit is another and not the ſame. And that it is an old ſtatute thou ſhalt know, that thou haſt ſpoken in thy own name, and what thou haſt learned by Tradition; but in Chriſt all the law and the Prophets is fulfilled and all ſtatutes who comes to witneſs him; he is the lawgiver, judg and king, and all is fulfilled as he comes to be witneſſed, and all ſtrange gods put away, even the Idols of gold and ſilver, and all falſe Prophets by him comes to be ſeen, judged, condemned and ſlain; and thou that would put it upon the Magiſtrate without to kill men by a law, and ſo to uſurp the power which is given to the Son, and ſo make them guilty of innocent blood, thou art a murtherer. And now to the further, who muſt judg of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, of hereſie, ſchiſm, and blaſphemy; I know thou denies Revelation and the reſt of the prieſts in <hi>England</hi> who trade with other mens words, and I know thou dare not ſay thou art infallible, and thou hath not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning of ſpirits, the Apoſtle exhorted them who dwelt in the light to try the ſpirits, but he bad not them who are led by the prince of the air, &amp; were children of diſobedience as thou art, of a covetous earthly mind, he bade not them to try, nor them who were carnal; and therefore ſtop thy mouth, thou cannot diſcern a lamb from a dog, nor a kite from a dove; and let all Magiſtrates who fear the Lord, either in this Nation or elſwhere take heed how they judg of hereſie &amp; blaſphemy: not that I am ignorant, but that there is hereſie and blaſphemy, but that none can judg who they are, but who have an iuſallible ſpirits therefore it is now as it hath bin, many have ſuffred as heretiques, as Chriſt for a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and the Apoſtles as ſetters forth of ſtrange gods, and were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted to death, and many do and are like to ſuffer by this ſpirit that dwels in <hi>Thomas Eliſon</hi> and therefore all you who are Magiſtrates, that ſit as Iudges and Rulers, take heed what you do, and take heed of zeal without knowledg, for ſo <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted, and ſo the Iews ſlew Chriſt the heir, and ſo many would have their will ſatisfied, but thou muſt be judged by all who dwell in the light<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and thou that ſitteſt as Iudg over
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118680:9"/>
another, ſee that thou be judged in thy ſelf; for to take your knowledge and dir<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction from ſuch as theſe men, in ſtead of planting you will be deſtroyers.</p>
            <p>And thou art offended at ſome that hold forth new lights and gifts, which thou ſayſt the word of God never taught us. <hi>Rep.</hi> All who are taught by the word which is eternal are guided in one light, for the light is but one; and this is no new lighr but the ſame that ever was. But thou that calls the letter the light, and the word, thou art blind, and art a hater of the light from which the Scripture was declared. And in the conclufion thou begs, that Scholers and Univerſities may be preſerved for the breeding of able Miniſters to preach the word and hold out the Sacraments; and this is the ſum of all that thou and the reſt of falſe Shepherds may be carried in the boſom of the Magiſtrates, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you, and deſtroy all that oppoſe you. As for Lrarning, it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, I own it in his place; but that it makes and breeds able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, I deny it, and all thoſe Miniſters; for many filthy frogs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirits have come out of the Univerſities, that have ſpread over the Nations as Locuſts without a King; and all their Preaching and their Sacramencs is carnal, and all their ability that is got by their trading leads people to be ſeven fold more the children of the devil. I ſpeak whaj I was a witneſs of wnilc I followed the chiefeſt of them. And therefore I ſay unto you who are Governors, hold not that up which the Lord hath curſed; for that which is natural cannot lead up to God; and therefore be ye all warned that you turn not back to build again that which God is deſtroying, and threw out the King and Biſhops, and one Parlament after another, and one power after another, becauſe they would needs limit the Lord o way to walk in. And truly God will pour you out from veſſel to veſſel, till you be emptied of all, and till you give him all power and honour to rule over his Church and people, that they may ſerve the Lord in freedom of ſpirit, and not in the fleſh; and if any walk dſſorderly, and break any righteous law, and walk in the fleſh, them execute your law upon, there is your place: But that yyu ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a way for God to walk in, he cannot, he will not be bound; and you that go about to limit him to any viſible appearance, ſhall be broken to peeces, for his glory he will not give to another:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>30 day 7 moneth:</date>
This was I moved of the Lord to write in Anſwer to Tho. Elliſon's Petition, and to the Magiſtrates.</dateline>
               <signed>A Lover of all thoſe that wait for the redemption of Iſrael; called after the fleſh Francis Howgill.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
